Inventory of the George F. W. Young papers
Hoover Institution Archives
George F. W. Young papers
1845-1994, 2012
2013C25
Hoover Institution Archives
13 manuscript boxes, 1 microfilm box (5.5 linear feet)
Photocopies of studies, government documents, business records, corporate reports, and other printed matter relating to German business investment in Latin America before World War II, and especially in the period before World War I, used as research material for journal articles by Young. Copies of some of Young's articles and his notes are also included.
Young, George F. W., 1937-
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2013.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical note
Born November 13, 1937 in Buffalo, New York, George Frederick William Young is an American-Canadian historian and Emeritus Professor of History at Saint Mary's University in Nova Scotia. Young received his bachelor’s degree from Harvard University, his master’s degree from the University of Freiburg in Germany, and his Ph.D. in 1969 from the University of Chicago. He spent some time in Chile from 1964 to 1965 studying as a Fulbright Scholar. Young then began his career in academia at the State University of New York at Buffalo as a lecturer in history in 1965. After achieving his doctoral degree, he became an assistant professor of history at Saint Mary’s University, where he would continue the rest of his career. Young is also an amateur musician and was, for a short time, CEO of a small utilities company in Northern Pennsylvania. He married in 1963 and has three children.
Scope and Contents note
The collection consists primarily of photocopies of printed matter (articles and book excerpts) and reproductions of archival materials from other repositories including, among others, the U.S. National Archives, the British Museum, the Weltwirtschafts-Archiv in Hamburg, and the Institut für Seeverkehr in Kiel, relating to German business investment in Latin America before World War II, especially in the period before World War I. Some of the articles Young wrote using these research materials are included, as are his notes.
Also included are seven microfilm reels containing selected documents relating to German banking and investment, dating from 1845-1938. These documents were used as research material for journal articles by Young.
Banks and banking--Germany.; Germany--Commerce--Latin America.; Investments, German--Latin America.; Latin America--Commerce--Germany.
- Inventory of printed source material for research on German banking, investment, trade, and business in Latin America, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
- German business in Latin America printed matter (Box 1-9)
  Scope and Contents note
  Photocopies of articles, papers, and monographs collected at conferences and in German research libraries.
  - Albert, Bill. "The Impact of WWI on Foreign Investment in South America: Brazil and Argentina,", 1989 July (Box-folder 1: 2)
    Paper read at the International Colloquium on Foreign Loans, Debt and Economic Development in the 19th and 20th Centuries, Universidade Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP), 18 pp.
  - Arndt, Paul. Deutschlands Stellung in der Weltwirtschaft. Leipzig: B.G. Teubner, 129 pp., 1908 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Arndt, Paul. Neue Beiträge zur Frage der Kapitalanlage im Auslande. Zeitschrift für Socialwissenschaft, N.F. IV, pp. 158-174, 215-224, 377-387, 445-460, 1915 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Arndt, Paul. Wesen und Zweck der Kapitalanlage im Auslande. Zeitschrift für Socialwissenschaft, N.F. III, pp. 1-19, 99-110, 173-194, 1912 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Bank-Archiv. Zeitschrift für Bank- und Börsenwesen, Berlin (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Helfferich, [Karl]. "Richard Koch." Jahrgang 7, Nr. 9 (February 1), pp. 129-135; Nr. 23 (September 1), 1908
    - Bloem, A.W. "The Foreign and Colonial Banks in London." Jahrgang 9, Nr. 12, pp. 186-188, 1910 March 15
    - von Gwinner, Arthur. "Kriegsanleihen." Jahrgang 14, Nr. 15, pp. 357-360, 1915 May 1
    - Helfferich, Karl. "Auslandswerte." Jahrgang 10, Nr. 14, pp. 209-216; von Brandt, M. "Die Einführung ausländischer Anleihen an deutschen Börsen vom Gesichtspunkt der auswärtigen Politik des Deutschen Reiches," pp. 221-223, 1911 April 15
    - Pudel, Siegfried. "Der Wiederaufbau des deutschen Ueberseebankwesens." Jahrgang 24, Nr. 7, pp. 178-181, 1927 January
  - Bank für Chile und Deutschland. "Jahres-Berichte, 1896-1915, 1917/1919 (1914 censored)." Hamburg, 1897-1920 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Barroso, Gustavo. Brasil – Colonia de Banqueiros (História dos emprestimos de 1824 a 1934). 6th ed., Rio de Janeiro: Civilização Brasileira S.A, 259 pp., 1937 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Benfey, Fritz. Die neuere Entwicklung des deutschen Auslandsbankwesens 1914-1925. Berlin, 252 pp. and fold-out chart, 1935 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Bergier, Jean-François. "Alfred Escher und die 'Revolution im Bankenbereich.'" Alfred Escher Ausstellung … am Hauptsitz der Schweitzerischen Kreditanstalt, Zürich, pp. 30-39, 1994 April-August (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Bieber, León Enrique. Las relaciones económicas de Bolivia con Alemania, 1880-1920. Berlin: Colloquium Verlag, 138 pp. with index, 1984 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Bieber, León Enrique. "Las relaciones militares entre Alemania y Bolivia, 1900-1935,", 1991 July (Box-folder 1: 12)
    Paper read at the 47th International Congress of Americanists, New Orleans, 42 pp.
  - Börsen-Enquete-Kommission. "Statistische Anlangen." Berlin: Reichsdruckerei, 1893 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Braunisch, Carl. "Der Wiederaufbau der deutschen Überseebanken nach dem Kriege." Breslau dissertation, 65 pp., 1927 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Broder, Albert. "L'expansion internationale de l'industrie allemande dans le dernier tiers de XIXe siècle: le cas de l’industrie électrique, 1880-1913." Relations internationals. No. 29, pp. 65-87, 1982 Spring (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Bott, Ernesto J.J. El Comercio entre los Estados Unidos y la América Latina durante la Gran Guerra. Buenos Aires: Librería de J. Menéndez, 359 pp., 1919 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - van der Borght, Richard. Das Wirtschaftsleben Südamerikas: insbesondere in seinen Beziehungen zu Deutschland. Cöthen: Otto Schulze, Vorbemerkung and Inhaltsverzeichnis only, 3 pp., 1919 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Bouças, Valentim F. História de Dívida Externa. 2nd ed., Rio de Janeiro: Edições Financeiras S.A., 368 pp. plus 9 pp. of tables, 1950 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Brasilianische Bank für Deutschland. "Hamburg—Brasilien, 1887-1812." Hamburg: Lütske u. Wulff, 39 pp., 1913 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Brasilianische Bank für Detuschland. "Jahres-Berichte, 1893-1919 (1914 censored)." Hamburg, 1894-1919 (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Brüning, Anton Paul. "Die Entwicklung des ausländischen, speziell des überseeischen deutschen Bankwesens." Heidelberg dissertation, 130 pp., 1907 (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Bonilla, Heraclio. "The Lessons of the Andean Countries with the External Debt Before World War I,", 1989 July (Box-folder 2: 4)
    Paper read at the International Colloquium on Foreign Loans, Debt and Economic Development in the 19th and 20th Centuries, Universidade Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP).
  - Canis, Konrad. "Der unmittelbare Übergang zum Imperialismus in Deutschland: Wandlungen in der Politik der herrschenden Klassen." Zeitschrift für Geschichte. Heft 10/1, East Berlin, pp. 957-970, 1982 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - de la Cavareda, Jose. Ricardo Donoso y Fanor Velasco: Historia de la constitution de la propriedad austral, pp. 89-137, 1834 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Chantriot, Émile. L’Allemagne et sa situation économique. Paris/Nancy: Berger-Lerault 7 Cie., 184 pp., 1910 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Collings, Harry T. "Die Kapitalexpansion der Vereinigten Staaten in Lateinamerika." Kieler Vorträge. No. 23, 24 pp., 1927 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Cortés Conde, Roberto. "The (Baring) Crisis of the 90s and the Argentine External Debt,", 1989 July (Box-folder 2: 9)
    Paper read at the International Colloquium on Foreign Loans, Debt and Economic Development in the 19th and 20th Centuries, Universidade Estadual de Compinas (UNICAMP), 38 pp. plus graph.
  - Crohn, H.F. "Argentinien im deutsch-englischen Wirtschaftskampf." Schmollers Jahrbuch. Jahrgang 39, Heft 2, pp. 223-256 [781-814], 1915 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Däbritz, Walter. David Hansemann und Adolph von Hansemann. Hrsg. von der Deutsche Bank, 165 pp. and name index, 1954 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - David, Hans. "Das deutsche Auslandskapital und seine Wiederherstellung nach dem Kriege." Weltwirtschaftliches Archiv. Band 14, pp. 31-70 and 275-300, 1919 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - De Montmorency, J.E.G. "The Black List." Problems of the War, Volume 3, 1918 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Delorme, Robert. "The Role of Foreign Investments in the Developmental Process: The Case of Mexico, 1884-1911." Tempe: Arizona State University, Center for Latin American Studies, 100 pp., 1975 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Der Friedensvertrag in 101 Forderungen: Was jedermann vom Friedensvertrag wissen muss. Berlin: Deutscher Volksblatt-Verlag, 32 pp., undated (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Dernburg, Bernhard. Kapital und Staatsaufsicht: Eine finanzpolitische Studie. Berlin: Ernst Siegfried Mittler u. Sohn, 51 pp., 1911 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Deutsche Bank. Geschäfts-Berichte / Annual Reports, 1908-10. Berlin, 1909-1911 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - "Banken, Eisenbahnen, Schiffahrt und Industrie." Deutsche Kultur in der Welt. 1. Jahrgang, Nr. 1/2 (January) and "Englands Krieg gegen deutschen Handel." Nr. 3 (July), 1915 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Deutsch-Südamerikanische Bank, 75 Jahre [1906-1981]. Hamburg: Deutsch-Südamerikanische Bank A.G., 29 pp., 1981 March (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Deutsch-Südamerikanische Bank. "Geschäfts-Berichte, 1907-1919 (1914 censored)." Berlin, 1908-1920 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Deutsche Überseeische Bank 1886-1936: Jubiläumsschrift. Berlin, 149 pp. (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Deutsche Überseeische Bank 1886-1961: Jubiläumsschrift. Berlin, 58 pp. (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Deutsche Überseeische Bank / Banco Alemán Transatlántico / Banco Allemão Transatlântico. "Geschäfts-Bericht 1909; Annual Reports (in English), 1914, 1915, 1917, 1918, 1919." Berlin, 1910, 1915-1920 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Deutsche Überseeische Bank. "Geschäfts-Berichte, 1890-1918." Berlin, 1891-1919 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Deutschland sei wach! Betrachtungen über Rüstungsfragen und Weltpolitik. Berlin: Deutscher Flotten-Verein, 1912 (Box-folder 3: 3)
    Vorwort, Inhaltsverzeichnis, Wert der deutschen Kapitalinteressen im Auslande pp. 146-149, and table Stärkevergleich der acht grössten Seemächte am 1. Januar 1912, pp.199-200.
  - Die Beschlagnahme, Liquidation und Freigabe deutschen Vermögens im Auslande, 1929 (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Die Deutschen Interessen in Argentinien, Chile, Bolivien und Peru: Eine der wichtigsten Fragen für Deutschlands Zuknuft. Von einem alten Praktiker. Berlin: Süd- und Mittel-Amerika-Verlag, 99 pp., 1911 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Die Diskonto-Gesellschaft, 1851 bis 1901. Denkschrift zum 50. Jährigen Jubiläum. Berlin (Box-folder 3: 6)
    Pages relating to Latin America: pp. 73-81, 124-129, 145, 208-212, 275-277.
  - "Die wirtschaftlichen Interessen Deutschlands in Südamerika." Nauticus Jahrbuch, pp. 323-352, 1903 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Diouritch, Georges. L’Expansion des Banques Allemandes a l'Étranger: Ses rapports avec le dévelopment économique de l’Allemagne. Paris/Berlin, 798 pp., 1909 (Box-folder 3: 8-10)
  - Drascher, Wahrhold. "Neue Grundlagen der Handelspolitik." Grundzüge der Wirtschaftsentwicklung in Süd- und Mittelamerika. Dritter Teil: Weltwirtschaft. Hrsg. von Franz Eulenburg. Munich/Leipzig, Duncker & Humblot, pp. 103-153, 1926 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Dresdner Bank Archiv (Frankfurt am Main): Geschäftsberichte der Dresdner Bank (pages relating to the Deutsch-Südamerikanische Bank), 1905, 1906, 1907, 1908, 1909. Deutsch-Südamerikanische Bank AG / Banco Germánico (Box-folder 3: 12)
  - Eckert, Christian. "Die Entwicklung der Schiffahrt zwischen Deutschland und Südamerika." Verhandlungen des deutschen Kolonialkongresses, pp. 962-975, 1905 (Box-folder 3: 13)
  - Economic Development of the Argentine Republic in the Last 50 Years. Buenos Aires: Ernesto Tornquist, Ch. XII, "The Public Debt," pp. 302-310, 1919 (Box-folder 3: 14)
  - "The Economic Weapon and Imperial Unity." The New Europe. Vol. 4, No. 73, pp. 225-233, 1918 March 7 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - The Electrical Industry in Germany: The Financial and Competitive Position. London: British Electrical & Allied Manufacturers' Association, 152 pp., 1926 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Ellinger, Bernard. "Value and Comparability of English and German Foreign Trade Statistics." Manchester Statistical Society, pp. [145]–158, 1904 (Box-folder 3: 17)
    Paper read 1904 March 9.
  - England's Financial Supremacy. London: Macmillan and Co., 106 pp., 1917 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Eulenburg, Franz. "Die Aufsichtsräte der deutschen Aktiengesellschaften." Jahrbücher für Nationalökonomie und Statistik. Dritte Folge, Band 32, pp. 92-109, 1906 (Box-folder 3: 19)
  - Fasolt, Friedrich. "Die sieben gröszten deutschen Elektrizitätsgesellschaften, ihre Entwicklung und Unternehmertätigkeit." PhD dissertation, University of Heidelberg. Borna-Leipzig, 59 pp., 1904 (Box-folder 3: 20)
  - Fernandez, Manuel A. "Patterns of British Business Expansion in Chile,", 1988 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    Paper read at the 46th International Congress of Americanists, Amsterdam. 54 pp. plus 28 pp. statistical appendix.
  - Forbes, Ian L.D. "German Commercial Relations with South America, 1890-1914." PhD dissertation, University of Adelaide, 321 pp., 1975 December (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Friedländer, Paul. "Die Expansion der deutschen Monopole in Lateinamerika." Einheit, Zeitschrift für Theorie und… [East Germany] 14. Jahrgang, Heft 12, pp. [1701]-1718, 1959 December (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Fritzsche, Heinrich. "Ausländische Anleihen auf dem deutschen Geldmarkte." PhD dissertation, University of Heidelberg. Leipzig, 126 pp., 1913 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - Fürst, Max. "Zum Verbot des amtlichen Börsenhandels." Die Bank, pp. 134-147, 1915 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Fürstenberg, Hans. Carl Fürstenberg: Die Lebensgeschichte eines deutschen Bankiers, 1870-1914. Herausgegeben von seinem Sohn. Berlin: Verlag Ullstein, 577 pp. with name index, 1931 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Funke, Alfred. "Südamerika und der Wiederaufbau deutsche Wirtschaft." Der Wiederaufbau. No. 33, Berlin, pp. 488-492, 1923 March 16 (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - García Mata, Carlos. "Expresión gráfica de hechos económicos: Los capitals extranjeros en Sud América." Revista de Economía Argentina. Año 2, No. 125, pp. 345-353, 1928 November (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Germany's Economic Forces. Presented by the Dresdner Bank, Berlin, on the Occasion of Its Fortieth Anniversary. Berlin, 1913 January 1 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Gini, Corrado. L'Ammontare e la Composizione della Ricchezza delle Nazioni. Torino, pp. 568-592 only, 1914 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - Grossweiler, Kurt. "Die Rolle der Grossbanken im Imperialismus." Jahrbuch für Wirtschaftsgeschichte. Teil III, Akademie-Verlag, [East] Berlin, pp. 35-55, 1971 (Box-folder 4: 11)
  - Gutsche, Willibald. Monopole, Staat und Expansion vor 1914. East Berlin: Akademie-Verlag (Akademie der Wissenschaften der DDR, Schriften des Zentralinstituts für Geschichte, Band 65), 304 pp. with index, 1986 (Box-folder 4: 12)
  - Harms, Bernhard. Zur Wiederanknüpfund und Pflege der weltwirtschaftlichen Beziehungen Deutschlands. Kiel: Institut für Seeverkehr und Weltwirtschaft, 86 pp, 1915 (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - Hartwig, Alfredo. "Die politische Stellungnahme der südamerikanischen Staaten im Weltkriege." Deutsche Rundschau. Jahrgang 44, pp. 329-350, 1918? (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Hauser, Richard. "Die deutschen Überseebanken." Jena dissertation, 36 pp., 1906 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Hayn, E. "Die Entwicklung der deutschen Elektrizitätswerke in Buenos Aires." Phoenix. (Buenos Aires), N.F. VI, Jahrgang 12, Heft 2, pp. 131-176, 1926 April 1 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Hell, Jürgen. "Das 'südbrasilianische Neu-deutschland.' Der annexionistische Grundung der wilhelminischen und nazistischen Brasilienpolitik, 1895-1938." Der deutsche Faschismus in Lateinamerika, 1933-1943. (East Berlin), pp. 103-124, 1966 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Hellauer, Josef. "Die Zahlungsvermittlung der englischen Banken im Überseehandel." Jahrbuch der Export-Akademie des K.K. Österreichischen Handels-Museums. 5. Studiejahre, 1902/03. Vienna, 91 pp., 1904 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Herbert, Lucien. "La puissance financière de l'Allemagne." Revue Hebdomadiare. Paris, pp. [5]-20, 1910 November 5 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Herz, Emil. "Deutschlands ausländische Banken." Annalen des deutschen Reiches, pp. 48-57, 1906 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Heyse, Theodore. "L'Allemagne et les finances Belges." Revue Belge des livres et documents à la guerre. Vol. 9, pp. 62-69, 218-237, 1933 (Box-folder 5: 9)
  - von Hirschfeld, Günther. Das Problem der deutschen Handels- und Wirtschaftsinteressen in Südamerika. Berlin: Verlag von Leonhard Simion NF, 23 pp., 1920 (Box-folder 5: 10)
  - Holleben, Baron von. "Capitales alemanes en la República Argentina." Revista de Derecho, Historia y Letras. XXVII, pp. [142]-145, 1906 (Box-folder 5: 11)
    Paper read to the Sociedad Colonial Alemana en Koenigsberg (Prusia), 7 June 1906.
  - Jacobs, Paul. "Die Zulassung von Wertpapieren zum Börsenhandel." PhD dissertation, Universität Berlin. Berlin: Universitäts-Buchdruckerei, 65 pp., 1914 (Box-folder 5: 12)
  - Jones, Charles A. "The British Investor and London Press Coverage of Argentine Affairs, 1870-90" and "European Bankers and Argentina, 1880-90." Cambridge University, Centre of Latin American Studies, undated (Box-folder 5: 13)
  - Joseph, Karl. Die Beschlagnahme ausländischer Wertpapiere. Berlin, 50 pp., 1920 (Box-folder 5: 14)
  - Kasdorf, Otto. Der Wirtschaftskampf um Südamerika. Berlin: Dietrich Reimer, 83 pp., 1916 (Box-folder 5: 15)
  - Katz, Friedrich. "Die deutschen Kriegsziele in Lateinamerika im ersten Weltkrieg." Wissenschaftliche Zeitschrift der Humboldt-Universität zu. [East Berlin], Jahrgang 13, Heft 7, pp. 875-879, 1964 (Box-folder 5: 16)
  - Katz, Friedrich. "Einige Grundzüge der Politik des deutschen Imperialismus in Lateinamerika, 1898 bis 1941." Der deutsche Faschismus in Lateinamerika, 1933-1943. East Berlin: Humboldt Universität, pp. 9-69, 1966 (Box-folder 5: 17)
  - Kleeberg, John Martin. "The Disconto-Gesellschaft and German Industrialization: A Critical Examination of the Career of a German Universal Bank, 1851-1914." PhD dissertation, University of Oxford, 1987 (Box-folder 5: 18)
  - Krauel, R. "Deutsche Interessen in Brasilien." Hamburg: L. Friederichsen, 30 pp., 1900 (Box-folder 5: 19)
    Vortrag gehalten am 9. Januar 1900 in der Abtheilung Hamburg der Deutschen Kolonial-Gesellschaft.
  - Lansburgh, Alfred. "Deutsches Kapital im Auslande" and "Der Staat und die Auslandsanleihen." Die Bank, pp. [820]-853 and pp. [623]-637, 1909 and 1913 (Box-folder 5: 20)
  - Lange, Ludwig. Expansion und volkswirtschaftliche Bedeutung deutscher Überseebanken. Karlsruhe, 64 pp., 1926 (Box-folder 5: 21)
  - Lehfeldt, R. A. The Rate of Interest of British and Foreign Investments. Vol. 76, Part 2, pp. 196-206, 1913 January (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Levy, Maria Bárbara. "Foreign Loans, Debt and Development: Brazil 1850-1913,", 1989 (Box-folder 6: 2)
    Paper read at the International Colloquium on Foreign Loans, Debt and Economic Development in the 19th and 20th Centuries, Universidade Estadual de Campinas (UNICAMP), July 1989, 28 pp.
  - Lewis, Colin. "British Business in the Argentine,", 1988 (Box-folder 6: 3)
    Paper read at 46th International Congress of Americanists, Amsterdam, July 1988, 84 pp.
  - London and River Plate Bank. "Report for 1912." London, 3 pp., 1912 November (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - Lück, Karlheinz. "Die Entwicklung der englischen, deutschen und nordamerikanischen Bankinteressen in Südamerika." Wirtschaftshochschule dissertation. Berlin, 137 pp., 1938 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - Lufft, Hermann A. L. "Argentiniens Nachkriegsentwicklung und das auswärtige Kapital." Chronik und Archivalien. Section VI, pp. 206-215, 1926 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - Lutz, Hermann. Deutschfeindliche Kräfte im Foreign Office der Vorkriegszeit. Berlin: Quaderverlag, 43 pp., 1932 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - Mann, W. (Weimar). "Der Anteil der Deutschen an Landwirtschaft, Industrie und Handel Lateinamerikas." Lateinamerika. Nr. (A) 91/92, pp. 1747-1750, 1927? (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Manual of Argentine Loans: National, Provincial, Municipal. Buenos Aires: Ernesto Tornquist & Co., 273 pp., 1930 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Manual of Argentine National, Provincial, and Municipal Loans, 1913. Buenos Aires: Ernesto Tornquist & Co., 115 pp. plus tables, 1913 December (Box-folder 6: 10)
  - Martin, Percy F. Handbook to Latin-American Investments.... London: Oliver and Partners, 90 pp., 1909 (Box-folder 6: 11)
  - Meding, Holger M. "Ethnizität, Identitäten und Migrationen der deutschprachigen Siedler in Missiones (Argentinien),", 1994 (Box-folder 6: 12)
    Paper read at the 48th International Congress of Americanists, Stockholm, 4-9 July 1994.
  - Meissner, Jochen. "Breakdown or Continuity? The Impact of the First World War on the Structure and Amount of German Investment in Latin America,", 1994 (Box-folder 6: 13)
    Paper read at the 48th International Congress of Americanists, July 1994, Stockholm/Uppsala, 21 pp.
  - Messner, Dieter. "L'Etymologie Portugaise Selon John Minsheu,", undated (Box-folder 6: 14)
  - Mewes, Friedrich Wilhelm. "Die Entwicklung des mexikanischen Bankwesens, speziell der deutschen Bankgründungen in Mexiko." Hamburg law dissertation, 1920 (Box-folder 6: 15-16)
  - Miller, Rory. "The Nature and Implications of British Investment in Latin America, 1870-1950: A Reappraisal,", 1994 (Box-folder 6: 17)
    Paper read at conference at Hamburg, 37 pp.
  - Minelli, Pablo M. Las inversions internationals en America Latina. Buenos Aires: Claridad, 109 pp. and index, 1939 (Box-folder 6: 18)
  - Model, Paul. Die grossen Berliner Effektenbanken.... Jena: Verlag von Gustav Fischer, 193 pp., 1896 (Box-folder 6: 19)
  - Mulhall, M.G., and E.T. Mulhall. Handbook of the River Plate Comprising the Argentine Republic, Uruguay, and Paraguay. 5th ed., Buenos Aires, banking section, pp. 870-93, 1885 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Náñez Falcón, Guillermo. "Commercial and Agricultural Activities of Germans in Guatemala, 1871-1914,", 1991 (Box-folder 7: 2)
    Paper read at the 47th International Congress of Americanists, New Orleans, July 1991 26 pp.
  - Neuhaus, Erich. "Die deutschen Kapital-Anlagen im Ausland." Deutsche Wirtschafts-Zeitung, cols. 37-41, 1906 (Box-folder 7: 3)
  - Newton, Ronald C. and Christel K. Converse. "The Response of Chilean and Argentine Deutschtum to the Third Reich: A Comparative Examination,", 1991 (Box-folder 7: 4)
    Paper read to the 47th International Congress of Americanists, New Orleans, July 1991, 21 pp.
  - Norddeutsche Bank in Hamburg. "Jahresberichte, 1886-1918." Hamburg, 1887-1919 (Box-folder 7: 5)